[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio net se radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software hello this is to be as
for software engineering radio today
I've got with me the two co-authors of
the new book SBT in action josh silat
and matthew father welcome to the show
hi great to be here although some of our
listeners might know you already through
past books and talks I'd like you to say
some sentences about yourselves who you
are and what you're doing sounds good hi
I'm I'm Josh surrett I am a senior
software engineer at typesafe we're the
company behind Scala acha play I'm
currently the tech lead for the building
automation team internally we call it Q
because we like James Bond
I guess that is great so you're kind of
a playing like like playful company and
other companies like that yeah yeah plus
I mean the the term building automation
is a little flexible in terms of what we
do so my team's kind of the whenever
there's some emergency to put out we try
to do it for other teams kind of thing
right right and Matthew hi my name is
Matthew Farwell I work for next thinking
Lausanne in Switzerland I'm a member of
the SAS team there so I have a generally
I've worked on open source projects
before I've contributed I have a general
interest in code quality and the lead on
the scala style project which is a
static checker for scala so how come you
both got together to write a book on SBT
yeah I guess it was I'm trying to
remember what year this was but
essentially I was doing a lot of SVT at
work I had just swapped from being
mostly a maven guy
and had to start picking off some SBT
and at the time SBT was really hard to
learn really hard to learn but I kind of
fell in love with the build tool at work
like having to use it every day and
seeing the power that it had so I really
felt that it needed a book and that it
needed a book to kind of talk about core
concepts so I went out seeking
co-authors yeah and then I I don't
remember how we actually got introduced
Matthew but I know that but Matthew
works in the the office below the
typesafe office in Switzerland this is
true
I actually proposed another book a
different book on testing tools to
Manning and they said well we're not
really very interested in that at the
minute but how about this one over here
on on SBT because they knew that you
were looking for co-authors Josh and
then we got introduced I think we'd
known each other beforehand but we got
introduced formally for this book
through Manning right right so I think
we heard yeah we had met open source and
then yeah Manning is the one who put us
together for actually author in the book
exactly interesting before we are
actually diving in the topic of what is
SBT and what is written in your book I
would raise more general question which
is what is a build system in general
what is this and why do we need build
systems and what can we do with it okay
so the build system will give you a few
things
I'll give you reproducibility so the
problem is is that if you have one
developer who builds your product and
another develop builds the same product
they won't actually build the same
product so what you want your build
system to do is give you reproducibility
now this can be in a form of a something
simple as like a batch script or a shell
script or something like this or it can
be in a more formal build tool now the
point about a build tool is it gives you
experience gives you the other
developers experience saying okay so if
you do want this this way then it
becomes a more standard beast and you
can build on the shoulders of giants
yeah so I I actually have been working
on a blog article about what is a build
tool useful for and Matthew Matthew did
a great job with framing out chapter 1
which I of our book which really covers
why you need build tools but you know if
you look at it kind of historically what
we first started out with is exactly
what Matthew said you start out with
nothing and a developer would like run
you know C++ on a file and get a dot o
and then have to make that into a binary
and you want consistency so you want to
script this so you create a script that
does that what what I would I would
differentiate that as that is the build
the script and then when you move into
build tools you need to provide
something useful above and beyond just
scripting and that's where standing on
the shoulders of giants kind of fits in
somebody else has defined a basic you
know template for what C++ projects look
like this is true and for example
automate right you you run configure to
see what opera a computer has and then
you run make to actually build against
the libraries and things that exist on
that computer and its architecture and
that's a C++ style thing that that
design is forced upon you by the build
tool but the beauty is you don't have to
write all of it from scratch you're
using what other people have done good
ideas that they've put in there and
reusing them so that's kind of that's
kind of the build tool needs to
differentiate from the core and I would
say you need three components in build
tools of today the first component is
you need the ability to define higher
level tasks than the shell provides
these are things like here's a bunch of
source code go make me a binary out of
it you know here's a bunch of Java files
I want a jar here's a bunch of C++ files
I want a shared library for Linux that
sort of thing the second thing that
build build tools do nowadays that
that's kind of a mandatory is caching
the ability to not redo work this is
this is kind of the main advantage over
shell scripts these days is
you you if you have already compiled a
file and you don't want to have to
recompile it if necessary so that's kind
of a big thing now you've seen a lot of
really cool build systems come out like
the one from Facebook called
it's got a weird name but it's based on
Google blaze that has just really
amazing caching that's kind of new theme
build tools but the third thing you need
in a build tool is what I call
dependency management and these are
dependencies of tasks so knowing that
this task needs to run this other task
before it can run that's something you
get above and beyond shell scripts you
know guaranteeing that files exist
before you touch them but also
dependency management includes say
libraries you know like looking up
libraries that you would like to use
make and configure is another good
example
you need to look at the dependencies of
the system that you need before you
build the project so I would I would
argue that modern build tools are mostly
composed of three things you know this
extensible high-level tasks system
really really solid caching and then
dependencies dependencies across task
dependencies on the things on the
machine and dependencies on some sort of
ecosystem for your project
like you know ruby gems you need to
depend on those in your brakebills that
sort of thing so when you're saying
standing on the shoulders of giants and
do you think that you can have a
multi-purpose built system or do you
think single purpose-built systems are
good as well so you have this build
system for C files and the great build
system for Scala projects and things
like that or do you think there's a way
of having everything together in one
system so if I can take a shot at that
my my argument would be that the build
system will generally be better for the
language that it is written in mostly
because that's the language they're
using to write the build system so the
build authors see the issues there's
there's nothing inherently I would say
making a general-purpose build system
not feasible it's more a matter of the
amount of investment the community does
in it we we as software developers tend
to create communities around a
language or an ecosystem and to the
extent that people cross between these
ecosystems a build tool can cross
between the ecosystems but if those
ecosystems never cross you you kind of
miss out on having the same you know a
good experience in a general purpose
tool and not in the general purpose tool
for example the the JavaScript build
tools right now are super focused on
JavaScript the which as you know
javascript distributes a source so
there's a whole class of problems in in
SBT around creating binaries and caching
that the JavaScript tools never really
have to deal with and they can really
push the envelope in what they do things
that if you tried to push that in a
general purpose tool you'd have to undo
possibly some of the things that are
done for binary to go that far so I
guess my argument would be I like
general-purpose build tools a little bit
better but I find myself attracted to
whatever the most popular tool in that
ecosystem is so if I'm running C++ I
will use something like C make now if
I'm writing Scala I use SBT if I were
working for a Java only project I would
probably still use SBT but only because
it's the JDK okay sure okay - don't now
- your - SBT and why you brought the
book I'd like to ask you first what was
your life before SBT what build tools
did you use um yeah and why did you get
- yes between but personally for me I've
used pretty much everything I've used
maken and still using maven and Gradle
professionally but I also use SBT it's
I've been using all of them for a long
time basically okay and Josh I started
off with plain old make and oughta make
I
I fell in love with the - J option back
then for parallel make because I was I
was building for a distributed C cluster
thing
worked my way towards ant and then I
became really big into maven contributed
to a bunch of maven plugins for my
company we actually ran internal
releases of a bunch of maven plugins
like the maven JavaScript's plugin we
were early to the web 2.0 JavaScript
phase so we had invested a lot in maven
and Java scripts at that time and
contributed to the maven Scala plugin
and getting that sucker stable so yeah I
was I brought maven into two different
companies that I know of okay boom so
kind of a big history and a lot of
knowledge about build systems so having
talked about build systems what is SBT
then and where is the difference to
other build systems out there
I think the key the key differentiator
and SBT comes in comes in its evolution
SBT kind of started out with Scala
development was a little slow the
compiler took longer than Java and all
of the existing tools were designed for
a very snappy compiler where you can
literally run Java C by forking a
command line process and it doesn't take
too long
Scala was very different the compiler
does a lot more work so SBT kind of
started as experimentation in avoiding
compiling files for Scala and optimizing
the Scala compiler so one of the very
first things that did that
differentiated it from other Java tools
at the time was it remained resident in
memory as its default mode of operation
so you kick it off as a process that
interacts on the terminal and it tries
to keep the compiler warm in a in in a
class loader so that the the java
optimizations that have been applied to
those classes remain in place for your
project for as long as possible so that
was kind of the core architectural
differentiator that started with SBT and
then it turned out that it its
performance for Scala was that much
better than other build tools that
people just kind of in the Scala
community flocked to it so now we talked
about what's SBT
what is it not so do you see any
boundaries something where you say okay
SPT is going this far and and it's not
really multi-purpose and the answer to
any question it's a good question you
know III would say that SBT can be
multi-purpose again I would say the the
fact that everything in it is written in
Scala and kind of pushes you to write
something JVM related kind of kind of
necessitates that it will always be
associated with people who are using the
JVM or using Scala even even the C++
support that's been contributed there's
there's a C++ plug-in that creates a C++
life cycle these are people who are
using C++ to you know make j'ni
libraries so I kind of see the ecosystem
kind of always been that one thing I
also say with SBT is SBT is designed for
moderate sized projects and having these
fragmented up so it's not designed there
there's some companies that are really
pushing heavy on these monolithic
repositories where you put all of your
code into one giant repository for you
know five to ten thousand engineers SBT
is definitely not that and it's not
really going that direction it's mostly
about moderate size projects the the
ability to really have an elegant
interactive experience for for a team
for what they work on and then you
coordinate your packages and
distribution and stuff with some other
external tool something like a team city
and say an artifact turi or a nexus
repository so that's that's kind of
where the SBT is not meant to scale up
to tens of thousands of massive projects
it's really meant to take your team and
make them as productive as possible for
the project they're working on and you
leverage other things to coordinate
further as you said there had been some
development going on on what is SBT and
how SBT is dealing with the project
could you maybe elaborate a bit on
the evolution of SBT and on what changed
over the time and where we were four
years ago and where we are now sure so
four years ago the SBT but like I said
started off as an experiment and how
fast you can make Scala compilation and
I think largely it succeeded in being
the best in that space to the point that
the the maven plug-in now uses the
incremental compiler from SBT their
support for ants and Gradle has pulled
in the the incremental compiler from SBT
and I believe the other the other things
but basically anyone who's doing
anything with Scala is going to be using
a fragment of SBT for the for the Scala
compiler if they're not that users
probably are complaining so so that's
kind of kind of where it started off
with the core originally SBT had a user
facing syntax that was meant to be
object-oriented so for example the
default build was a trait where all of
the settings were you know members of
this trait that you could extend an
override previous values but we actually
ran into significant limitations here if
you wanted to write a plugin for SBT you
would create a new trait and/or class it
had usually had to be a trait and you
would extend the default build and add
your own behavior the problem we had is
as soon as somebody made something final
in the class hierarchy that would
prevent anyone else from touching that
setting ever again and there are all
sorts of also it turns out that there
was a lot of confusion around object
initialization order and when things
would instantiate and what you could
depend on and that sort of thing with
that style of syntax where you try to
make everything just be an object that
and pretty much nothing no one else was
doing that in the space of making making
a bill just be objects if they were they
were using lots of dynamic tricks to
kind of read
their tasks on the side so that someone
else could manipulate them later
whereas SBT was trying to remain as much
as possible a statically compiled so
this led to a massive revision to the
the user syntax and that happened
between SBT 0.7 and SBT 0.9 and the new
syntax that you see with these deferred
initialization blocks and defining tasks
and keeping track of dependencies
between things and being able to
override any setting that was defined by
anyone ever is is really what makes SBT
have the whole convention over
configuration mindset and really gives
it the flexibility to be a
general-purpose build tool so that was
kind of a significant change in its
history yeah I realized that a lot and
played around with with SBT for some
time and saw that move and I was really
glad that you finally managed to write a
book about it cuz I was kind of confused
by what can I do now
and and how can I do it and how does the
syntax actually work and and why do I
have to do this and not then and stuff
like this so I'm really glad he came to
a point where he said okay let's write a
book about it but I guess that was not
your motivation of doing of writing the
book what was your motivation why did
you write a book I wrote it because
learning it initially was actually
somewhat difficult because of the poor
documentation so I felt that they
deserved a book people needed to know
how to learn it so that's actually the
the primary reason why I wrote the book
was to serve as a more a gentler
introduction than what the the website
covers the website kind of the SBT
documentation you have a getting started
guide which kind of you know gets you
started and then leave
hanging and then you have the in-depth
guide where you kind of have to already
know a good bit about SPT to read the
details to get specifics and there
wasn't something in the middle that kind
of takes you from beginner to
intermediate so you could read the
advanced documentation so that's
primarily why I wrote the book I had
spent six months doing that myself the
hard way and I felt like no one else
should have to do it the hard way thank
you very much for them for me it was
pretty much the same is I I couldn't
find any good online documentation about
SPT and I'd had trouble learning it
myself and basically everything Josh
just said okay bye right while reading
through books I saw this great and
interesting reference to Emma's excel on
some parts of your book when you were
talking about setting settings or
definitions you wrote about how you
would put the values in Emma's Excel
columns why did you do that and what is
the the reason behind that we actually
we actually had a lot of interesting
feedback on that section it's it's one
of those sections that people either
loved or hated but the the ms-excel
section is specifically because I think
Emma's Excel is the most familiar
functional program and environment of
any developer out there so even even if
you've never touched a functional
programming language you've probably had
to do excel at some point in your life
and it gives you a lot of the
fundamental concepts of what people try
to attain with functional programming
you know for example if you if you want
to compute data you need to create a new
cell that contains the results of the
computation and then if you want to use
that again you have to reference the
previous cell that you just created for
the next computation and that that
notion is you know quite simple but it
when you're trying to describe a lot of
the reasons for doing things or how it
works under the covers just the most
people can see the MS Excel spreadsheet
but if I were to use the terms from
functional programming probably it would
just sound like I was being pompous
okay interesting approached though
really liked it and I guess people will
definitely understand what you were
talking about the topic and in this
chapter going a bit deeper into SBT you
have this chapter on core concepts of
SBT and if you want I'd like to split
them up between you two and the first
will be the initialization czar codes
what does that mean
so initializations our code this is a so
there's a phase and a build when it is
loading one thing that's interesting if
if you were to compare SBT with like
rake or Gradle Ray both rake and Gradle
when they run through the build file
they are directly manipulating some some
built state somewhere where they are
like pushing tasks into the build state
or altering configuration in the build
state in SBT we didn't really want this
this dynamic nature we wanted to be able
to inspect who had touched something and
what had happened but you need this
programmatic ability to alter build
State so we created this thing called
initializations and an initialization is
essentially a function that runs when
the build is slowing that starts it's a
block of code that will do things to the
build state that's what initialization
is but in addition to just running the
function it manually keeps track of all
the dependencies that that you're
touching in the build state so if you
wanted to run the inspect command in SBT
you can actually see which settings
affect other settings you can see if I
if I want to affect compile here the
settings which it uses from its
initializations
and and touches so here's the setting
that I configured to touch things it's
meant to give you the the kind of
visibility that you want out of static
analysis is what what that's all about
okay you use the word settings
what is a setting and why is there a
difference between
and a definition so uh the SBT build
format basically has two things that you
can you can define in it besides besides
import statements you can import you
know libraries and things or plugins
there are settings in there definitions
so a definition is like a raw Scala
method or a value you can define these
these are static they're initialized as
part of the class that the build is but
it's literally just raw Scala code
that's instantiated as if it were in a
static object and so that that's you
know convenience things and stuff but
not something you're really going to be
manipulating by the build but it's very
useful to have helper methods and the
other the other critical thing for
definitions is defining new items in the
build state of SBT so SBT is all key
value based you have keys and keys have
values you can define a new key and we
have open extension so if I want to
store a new value for example for C++ of
what the arguments are for C++ I can
define a new setting key that will store
a sequence of strings which are the
arguments to the C++ compiler that
someone can define later so I can or
someone can set later I should say so I
can define the key as a value that
people can make use of later in the
build that's a definition a setting is
something that manipulates the built
state a setting is something that can be
rerun if needed and tracks its
dependencies so the idea here is if I
set the C++ compiler flags there's going
to be a setting that says this key
should have this value and I want to
keep track of where those values come
from not only which build file so if you
run an inspect on the C++ Keys you can
see which build files set the key you
should also be able to see if other
settings are contributing to it so for
example the C++ flags that I pass might
actually be defined by the architecture
flag for what I want to build for so it
I should be able to know that it depends
on the architecture flag and I should be
able to change the architecture flag
dynam
and recompute the new c++ Flags because
I kept track of this dependency
relationship um this is where that Excel
example comes in you know in Excel if I
change the value of a cell the other
cells that depend on it are updated
automatically this is the same case with
SBT because we're tracking dependencies
between how we compute a value and
that's the setting system and the
initialize system that's what that does
you you want to put a value in a key but
we're gonna remember how you computed it
so we can do some optimizations and use
so you can dynamically change your build
and and and kind of try out different
things another another good example is
for instance the compilation options for
the compile compilation and the test
compilation are related and one inherits
from the other so for instance when you
when you're compiling your test code
you're actually using the settings that
come from your compile code plus extra
ones for the test ones all right yeah
but then you have to kind of know the
place you have to write your settings to
or your your your definitions to and
your values where to add so you can have
kind of have to define beforehand the
slots where you can write your
information at and can't really do it on
there on a later step of the build yeah
this is this is actually I would say one
of the hardest aspects of learning SBT
is knowing where to put your settings
initially in in the book we have a whole
chapter where we just literally I call
the chapter the inspect chapter SBT has
a command called inspect where you can
look at a task or look at a setting and
see what it depends on and this is the
most valuable tool in all of SBT is I I
want to change how compile runs I can go
read the SBT Doc's and maybe the answers
in there but if I run inspect I can
follow the dependencies of the build and
figure out where the setting is that I
need to touch and that's that's in my
opinion one of the greatest beauties of
SBT is any built you sit down to will
have custom content in it but I can
inspect the build and learn where to put
my change it might take me a little
while but I can figure it out and so you
know in the book we have I guess it's
not chapter three anymore it's chapter
four but there is a chapter which tries
to go through the default build to give
you a notion of where to look to put
your settings where where to assign
things to make sure they show up but it
is that is the most difficult aspect of
learning SBT or defining like a default
build is saying this should be an
extension point that people will use I
need to document this or this won't be
an extension point you know if all else
fails you can redefine a task with your
own value but you want to allow people
to reuse default behavior and just
configure it to work the way they want
as opposed to reimplemented as much as
possible and how does this affect this
this other great aspect and I think
unique aspect of SBT which is parallel
execution of tasks how does this affect
it it's it's a great enabler of it
essentially if you can if you can track
all of the dependencies and force all of
them to be known you can compute your
task graph in parallel but SBT you know
make actually forced you to do this in
in a make file a core make file one of
the reasons people get annoyed with them
is if you wanted to build a project you
had to explicitly list out all of your
source files make had to know all of the
inputs exactly and all of the outputs
and make could run in parallel because
you had explicit these files produce
this file these files produce this file
and you knew all of the dependencies and
you can compute a whole graph in SBT we
do the same thing where we know all of
the dependencies the only thing that
that people get tripped up on is ena and
SBT tasks if you are touching a file
your task needs to return that file if
you are going to modify a file you
should actually create a new file with
the modifications because otherwise
you're actually breaking this whole
notion of parallelism it's it's one of
these general rules of parallelism if
your data is immutable it's really easy
to paralyze an SBT we can know all the
depends
is between tasks run them in parallel
but the file system is this giant
mutable variable that sometimes you can
screw up so I wish we had done more to
kind of clean that up
but the really beautiful thing of
knowing dependencies is you can run
things in parallel across the graph you
can run two different compiles at the
same time if you know they have
different target directories and we have
that enabled by default as opposed to
most other build tools it's not the
default you have to enable it that
actually led to a lot of interesting
interesting things early in the
evolution of SBT it was a lot harder for
plug-in writers to get started because
they had to they had to know how to
program concurrently they had to deal
with the parallelism right away the
beautiful thing though is our ecosystem
has benefited now we have parallelism by
default and plug-in authors have had to
learn how to write parallel safe code so
the whole ecosystem now can be run in
parallel which is interesting because
then standing on the shoulders of giants
actually works because you know how it
works and just can run your task and
don't have to think that much compared
to two years ago or whatever which is
nice yeah the the setting system is
designed to make this this this notion
of parallel tasks easier by tracking the
dependencies explicitly that helps a lot
it you know but parallel code is still
parallel code they're still they're
still it's still hard but we definitely
try to make it as simple as we possibly
can
yeah yeah let's go to a more easy to
understand topic which is dependency
management why didn't you come up or why
didn't the SBT people come up with a
different solution than IV that's that's
historically at the time when SBT was
pulling in a dependency manager IV was
the only game in town
unless you were using maven itself a
third did not exist yet Gradle Gradle I
guess was coming around but they were
still using IV so the IV was basically
the only game in town the dependency
manager I like IV is a great idea
in his model the actual implementation
leaves a lot to be desired and I would I
think most build tools have have
abandoned ivy over the course of time
it's probably the the Ivy related
aspects of SBT are the most of the bugs
that I have to deal with an SVT are
around ivy so that's unfortunate
but the good news is we actually just
launched we're launching a new milestone
where we rewrote a core portion of ivy
to use aether so if you resolve if you
resolve maven dependencies you'll use a
third if you resolve Ivy dependencies
you use Ivy what the the reason why SVT
is still stuck on IB is but for its core
is actually the Ivy model is a lot more
comprehensive and a lot more elegant
than the maven model an SVT makes use of
these these the the the nicer dependency
graph that IB has so we couldn't just
wholesale gut ivy and replace it with
aether that just that that wouldn't
happen at one point in time we had been
talking with Gradle about sharing the
dependency manager solution but that
kind of fell through so instead there
were a couple different tasks that
happened there's a new the SBT kind of
rewrote the resolve engine for IB to try
to improve its caching and performance
and we gutted all of the maven related
code out of IB and are instead using a
third for Ivy both of those features are
experimental in the current release of
SBT but I expect them to stabilize and
kind of be the new dependency management
solution for wound on o for those of you
who aren't familiar with the ivy Ivy's
dependency management the the real key
difference between it and maven is this
notion of a configuration and
configurations of beautiful things you
can you can have a a module like you
know a commons logging module and you
can define a configuration called
default that has the commons logging jar
in it so if people depend on you they
get this default configuration they get
the logging jar but if you have like an
internal project in the logging API
where you want to reuse
some testing code from logging you can
actually say I depend on Commons logging
I want their compiled their default
configuration to be part of my compiled
configuration and I want their test
configuration to be part of my test
configuration and what this means is
when we resolve your test dependencies
we will grab the actual test jars of you
know Commons logging with the the
regular jar of Commons locking and we'll
put the test jar on the test glass bath
in the other jar on the other classpath
and this is kind of a built in feature
and you can have transitive dependencies
in this fashion so comments logging test
jars can depend on other testing
libraries like let's say it uses some
sort of easy mock or something
if the Commons logging test dependency
depends on easy mock that shows up
transitively in maven if you use
classifiers you can get a jar from a
third-party dependency but there's no
transitive notion you don't get to see
further down the stack of what what you
might need so there's there's a bit of a
limitation there whereas with IV you
actually see this all transitively the
downside is then resolution is a little
bit harder to catch and takes a little
bit longer plus the actual
implementation of IVs resolution is
generally inefficient to begin with so
that that's kind of been - like I said
it's been a massive pain point for SBT
but there are some really cool features
SBT has that are specific to this
configuration notion one as an example
one of my favorites is Scala Scala
actually supports compiler plugins so
you can you can actually have a plugin
to the Scala compiler which alters how
things compiler compile there's a few
things that use this there's there's
things that do static code analysis
where they will literally just sit
beside the compiler while the compiler
runs and kind of issue additional
warnings that these are you know the
linting tools and that sort of thing
there's there's some which actually
rewrite your code so when it sees a cent
tree it will try to rewrote it rewrite
it to be more performant the the one
that I like there is the OpenCL plugin
will actually try to rewrite collection
based code to you know use OpenCL and
and the the cool supercomputing stuff
from that or hyper I don't know it's not
really super Computing's graphics engine
computing I don't know it's crunchy so
yeah so these plugins are dependencies
that your project has to compile but
they're not dependencies like on any of
the standard maven class paths
so what SVT is done is its created this
new configuration called Esper called
think it's scala c plugin is the name of
the configuration and you can define
dependencies where you say Maya Scala
see plug-in configuration depends on
these things and when Ivy goes to
resolve it gets all of it together
so if I have dependencies that bump my
Scala to 11 3 2 to 11 for this will also
affect my compiler plugins if necessary
it kind of all happens in this big
bundle so that's that's kind of the the
nice aspect of it whereas if we were to
do this with say a third we'd literally
need to have two separate notions of of
module or artifacts we'd have to have
one for the dependencies you compile
with and we have to have another notion
of artifact for the Scala compiler
plugins we'd have to run resolution
twice yeah so essentially we've we've
kind of locked ourselves into the this
model of how to do dependencies in SVT
because we really liked it okay yeah
totally understood this and we'll see
how that goes in in future releases then
you both touched a lot Gradle and maven
and make and we talked about them for
various reasons a general question which
came up a lot after I asked around what
to talk about with you is where is the
difference between Gradle and maven and
make and why would you use SBT over
Gradle and and is there a situation
where you would say okay let's use
Gradle here or even make or C make or
whatever
okay so for me the Dara the the
fundamental difference between maven and
something like Gradle and SBT is the
maven is a declarative build system so
what you specify in your palm which is
where you where you to clay your built
is you say okay I want this plug-in to
run and this plug-in to run and this
plug-in to run and it says okay I've got
a number of phases I'm going to fit your
compiled into this phase okay so it
prepares the resources compacted that
then compiles your Java is then packages
your Java and you can say okay I want a
particular plug-in to run in a
particular phase and you you're
declaring the set of things that you
want to do using XML so you're using an
existing plug-in and you're defining
your your your build depending on XML
with Grayling's and SBT your tasks are
actually defined not in XML but they're
defined in either groovy for Gradle or
scala for SBT so you have access it's
it's a fundamentally different model as
in the SBT in the Gradle you have access
to actual real code so if you in you one
of your tasks in your Gradle or SBT
build you want to copy a file you call a
method on a Java class which copies a
file in maven you have to do it fire a
plug-in so you have to have a plug-in or
you can do it one of using an existing
plug-in like that for instance as a
groovy plugin for maven and there's an
ant plugin for maven so maven is
declarative uses XML
whereas SBT in groovy our task-based and
they're actually written in code the
difference between groovy and SBT is
less clear as far as the builder itself
is concerned and concerned but Gredos
bit is written in groovy and SBT you
write your build file in scala so great
Gradle is actually written in Java since
the surface in taxes is groovy but what
one thing to add there with with maven I
want to throw an ant actually so
aunt was task-based but there's there's
a big difference between Gradle and
SPG's tax based system and aunts task
based system and that is that Gradle
will allow you to redefine a task an SBT
will allow you to redefine a task later
from some sort of default implementation
of a task right
so in ant you can define a task and then
that task is set for the ant build you
cannot change it there's also no default
available tasks to do standard things
when maven came around it provided this
common model where if you wanted to
compile a Java project here's how it
works if you didn't like how it worked
it got in your face and basically said
don't do this or you have to get really
dirty with plugins and that actually was
very healthy for the Java ecosystem to
try to push some standards and
conventions it turns out though that
everybody needs to do something custom
and depending on how custom you need to
go maven can either be you know a little
bit of a pain but a really good friend
or it can be a huge pain and just
prevent you from actually getting stuff
done it really depends on how far you
deviate from that model because of how
the plugins work and that sort of thing
we also had a hell of a time getting
Scala to fit in the model because you at
the time you couldn't control plug-in
ordering and you couldn't control the
order in which plug-in tasks would run
interface they just would get appended
depending on how they were declared and
you couldn't change default so it was it
that was a mess
they sort of fixed that but it's still
some of the fundamental problems still
remain
what Gradle and spt add above that you
know is this ability to redefine a task
if I don't like the default compiled
task I can just throw my own in there if
I don't like the default test task I can
throw my own in there you know we have
we have we have clients that are using
Gradle we have clients that are using
SBT and we have clients that completely
customize their the entire lifecycle
their project all the way down to the
compiled tasks and that's that's
definitely something that's a little bit
easier to do in SBT in Gradle but it
also has that
you know default convention it's less
strict about it so there there's some
people that think this is a really bad
thing to be less strict about the
default convention to me it's a matter
of what you need in your company if you
really need to strictly enforce this is
how all Java projects were build maven
is a great option to really heavily push
that but if you need some flexibility
because you know things differ here and
there and you want to be able to do that
quickly a build tool like Gradle or SBT
or is a far better choice when it comes
to ant I still I hesitate to say
anything
mostly because I think the fact it
doesn't provide a default build is is
basically that it's only major fall at
this point you know like that's that's
the reason everyone started to abandon
it and go other places okay sure
and it's those huge XML files nobody
actually can read but this is only my
personal opinion on that well there was
there was one guy who could read it this
is the problem with ant is that you have
to read the XML to be able to tell what
the bill does yeah where is in maven at
least you've got an idea about what's
gonna go on yeah that's right that's
right and this is why is VT has inspect
is we want to you know it we have all
the same problems of dynamic tasking
from ant we inherit a lot of those so
you need you need new solutions to make
it viable you know like things like
Gradle and SBT it blends the notion of a
default build and convention and dynamic
tasks and so you kind of inherit the
problems of both of these systems that
you need to kind of work around yeah one
question that is connected in a way to
what you were liberating on is the the
question about conventions and maybe
having a build system that is
programmable and tweakable in any place
for like big and complex software so do
you think that there are build systems
that are great for for huge code bases
and then there are build systems that
are great for like micro services or
architectures like that but you need a
build system that is actually doing a
always the same things that anybody can
rely on this one thing I've been
thinking a lot about this we actually
have a this this like giant build system
and typesafe which builds you know a
couple million lines of code every night
of it's it's as much of the Scylla
ecosystem as we can build it once we
build and what what you do there is you
actually have to it's the microservices
approach where you make a micro build
for your team that is highly optimal for
your team where you put tasks in your
build that have nothing to do with
building the binary and have everything
to do with your team's productivity
these are things like like your test
tasks you might make custom tests tests
you might make custom integration tests
for your team but there's there's this
higher-level convention that you have
where if I call package on your you know
build I should get the package or if I
call you know install or deploy or
whatever you want to call it I will get
the package deployed somewhere and all
the tests you want me to run will be run
so you make a convention at a higher
level across builds but internal to your
team you want to make sure you're as
productive as possible where you need
this these customized things so I
actually personally believe in micro
service build with some sort of
architecture II a higher level build
that coordinates them I think this is
the best possible model to keep each
individual team as productive as
possible and make sure that your whole
or architecture an organization can work
together without dying if you allow
teams to deviate in everything then it's
really really really hard to organize
them together but I don't think the
restrictions that you make need to be as
as heavy as a lot of build tools kind of
push it when I when I worked at Google
it was they have a python-based built
tool and it's very similar to maven you
you define like I want a job a binary
and here's my input but you cannot
control at all how that how the compile
runs or any sort of individual
additional tasks if you wanted to create
you know something that would just run
run a little script here or there it was
kind of a pain in the butt and
developer productivity kind of suffered
because of that but overall developer
productivity was amazing in the sense of
they had really good caching across
teams you know they could share
artifacts and things I mean I'm a big
fan of trying to push this microservices
approach a little bit you know there's
more cognitive overhead when you have a
split layer like that but if you have a
company of 10,000 people you already
have split layers you already have a hot
you know some macro layers and some
micro layers going on anyway sure so
that that's that's my five cents how
about how about you Matthew well to be
quite honest I've not had that much
experience with the large massive builds
that you're that you're talking about
but if you have hundreds and hundreds of
these projects then you want everything
to be as similar as possible so it's
worth it at that point for instance you
could use maven because if everything is
the same then you you would have defined
your plugins to use to be Universal so
you you you probably wouldn't have a
problem and you'd want everything to be
exactly the same everywhere as much as
possible what we've done with this this
build tool typesafe that I was talking
about where I think I think we're at
like a million lines of code that we run
and test this is something which builds
the the nightly version of Scala with
including breaking language changes and
then rebuilds all of the the community
projects so you know all all the core
libraries that you rely on and it does
it every night and the the convention
that we had forced upon people inside of
SBT because right now it supports SBT
and it supports the Scala build the the
convention is every time you run publish
local all of your everything that you
need to build comes out of publish local
and into a ivy or maven repository
doesn't matter which one needs to go
into one of the two and every time we
call tests all the tests you care about
run so this this is actually in in the
community now if I go to any project and
I call tests I know all the tests that
they care about run and if I call
publish local I know all the jars that
they distribute are
cluded in there including if they want
to distribute you know tardy Jeezy's or
whatever deviant files or whatever that
has to get into the published local
phase but because we those are the only
two conventions we've applied to all of
the builds so internally they can do
whatever kind of crazy things they want
source generation whatever they even
database testing and that kind of crap
but at an aggregate we have we have a
common you know these two tasks are the
interface and it actually it's working
out really well if you want to prevent
people from going too crazy and make
sure those two tasks always work you do
need something which runs and enforces
that they work correctly the amount of
time it takes to get one of the projects
in Scala that wasn't using the system to
then use this system there's a is it's a
nonzero amount of time to push this
convention if they never had the
convention before right like you need
something that enforces the convention
the the beauty of maven today is it
already enforces the convention but I
really do think the notion of micro
service builds and these architectures
you know like something like team city
even as being these the up and coming
way of the future yeah and it's kind of
getting a working in line of the agile
movement and stuff like this so
independent teams and yeah so you have
those conventions on a higher level
which work well as well the other thing
I've never I've never really seen as
I've never seen one company only use a
single bill tool for everything I've
seen them try you know I've been in a
bunch that had these restrictions to
only use a single build tool and yet
there were lots of nested build tools
within that bill tool so so the you know
having having these conventions and
micro builds and micro services I feel
like it's it's a reality you can try to
push as far to one direction of away
from micro services or you can go too
far the other direction
but I think living in the middle is
actually a good place to be you know
they're they're they're trade offs but
I've never seen a successful company
with with just one build tool I should
say I haven't seen many
oh there may there may be
one or two out there but I don't think
I've you know even at Google where most
everything was blaze they were still are
turning their build tools there was
still little thing there were there
tricks that people would use to sneak
things inside of blaze and all sorts of
fun like that
so Asheville sure at the end of this
interview I'd like to ask you about the
repple like this read eval print loop
are you actually using this or is
because I didn't really get to too many
own to manage to to get my head around
this and why to use it that much and you
know why to actually program on the
command line are you using it and your
daily life who is using it and why are
you using it yes yes I use it almost
every day
Wow clearly yes and and what in what
areas and what are you doing with are
you actually coding scholar codes on the
wrapper or for what I using it yeah okay
well person person I use three types of
rebel let's let's the the actual scholar
Apple which you can just you know find
out the syntax for something or you know
just play around with something and make
sure that it's it's right before you put
it into to real code then there's the
SBT repple which is the scholar apple
but it adds all of your dependencies in
which is which is brilliant if you're in
a project because you can explore an
interface and you can excel k-o and you
can do tab completion and this sort of
thing for finding out method names and
that sort thing and then the third one
which I use as the which is an extension
of the wrapper really is the scholar IDE
worksheet which is like a wrapper but on
on a page and in editor in in in Eclipse
yeah which is every time you save it it
evaluates the whole sheet and you can
really really play with an interface to
do that and using that another cool
thing is and I do this a lot I don't
know if you if you've tried this Matthew
but you can you can start SBT with a
open port for debugging you can connect
to it via IntelliJ or
Eclipse and then you can in the repple
type in the code that you want to debug
so you type in the code at live execute
you guarantee what went into it and then
you can step through the method and see
what happened in your debugger so it's
this really super interactive I'm
writing code I'm evaluating it I'm
writing code you can evaluate it even
the debugger you can evaluate it in the
repple it takes programming to the next
level it's kind of it basically brings a
lot of the joys of dynamic programming
to the static world I would say okay
okay I can see that okay
I'll definitely try that on where can
people reach you if they want to talk to
you by you on Twitter and Google+ where
where is the main area people can reach
you for me Twitter okay Twitter for me
as well most active on Twitter great so
we'll link both Twitter accounts on the
page of course and your book will be out
in approximately March s Manning said so
I'm looking forward to actually having
it in my hands so thank you very much
you too for talking to me and I'm
looking forward to talking to you next
time sounds great thank you have fun
thanks for listening SC radio an
educational program brought to you by I
Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website @ SC -
radioman to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on itunes
mention a message us on twitter at se
radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team at se - radio net this and
all other episodes of se radio is
licensed under the Creative Commons 2.5
license thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]